American Academy in Rome
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Board of Trustees Records, 1897-1957, undated, Series 2:; (box 1-17; 15.32 linear ft.)
  - Records of Officers, 1897-1957, undated, 2.3:
    - Individual Trustees, 1902-1946, undated, 2.3.5:
      - James C. Egbert (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - CARR - COC (Box 14, Reel 5773)
        - Comfort, Howard, 1933-1942 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
          (includes observations on School of Classical Studies with suggestions regarding staff, curriculum, administrative responsibilities, fellows, Advisory Council business)
        - Committee on the School of Classical Studies, 1937-1942 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
          (correspondence about staffing, fellows, summer school, finances, suggested policies for fellowship competitions, opinions on proposal to establish a new Roman studies journal)
        - COR - DET (Box 14, Reel 5773)
        - Deutsch, Monroe E., 1927-1930 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
          (correspondence about appointment as annual professor in the School of Classical Studies and his subsequent inability to accept the assignment)
        - Dinsmoor, William B. (Trustee; Secretary), 1935-1942 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
          (correspondence concerning appointment of the annual professor in School of Classical Studies, Advisory Council, discussion about classical fellows using their stipends in America should war conditions prevent travel to Europe)
        - Duckworth, George E. (Secretary, Advisory Council), 1939-1942 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
        - DUN - FO (Box 14, Reel 5773)
        - Frank, Tenny (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1922-1925 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
          (correspondence concerning appointment of annual professor; housing for students, library, and staffing)
        - FRANKL - GR (Box 14, Reel 5773)
        - Guernsey, Roscoe (Executive Secretary), 1919-1942 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
          (includes updated biographical information collected from alumni, correspondence about housing for women, summer session, fellowship competitions, nominating committee business, Committee on the School of Classical Studies business, appointment of Professor in Charge of the School of Classical Studies, changes in method of appointing fellows establishment of Friends of the School of Classical Studies, finances, reports and project plans of individual fellows; "Suggested Plan for Temporary Closing" in Rome during World War II, with staff evaluation, and recommendations about whom to retain)
        - GUG - HAD (Box 15, Reel 5773)
        - Haight, Elizabeth Hazelton (Chairman, Advisory Committee), 1926-1939 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (includes correspondence concerning housing for women students, staffing, summer sessions, finances, fellowships, Friends of the School of Classical Studies, fundraising)
        - Hammond, Mason (Trustee; Professor in Charge of Classical Studies; Director of Summer Sessions; Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1937-1944 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (correspondence regarding his appointment, staffing, Greek trip, fellows, women students, his decision to return to Harvard, helping fellows obtain employment upon their return home, thoughts on improving quality and number of fellowship applicants, contributing colleges and universities, prizes)
        - HAR - JA (Box 15, Reel 5773)
        - Thomas Spencer Jerome Lectureship, 1923-1924 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (correspondence regarding the appointment of Professor John G. Winter to deliver the first Jerome lecture series at University of Michigan and the American Academy in Rome)
        - Johnson, Allan C. (Trustee; Professor of Classical Studies; Chairman, Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1926-1943 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (includes correspondence expressing Johnson's interest in being the Annual Professor, finances, activities of staff and students, staffing, Professor Van Buren, possible candidates for annual professorship, Greek trip, fellows, nominations)
        - KEE (Box 15, Reel 5773)
        - Kelsey, Francis W. (Trustee), 1921-1926 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (includes correspondence concerning fellows, Archaeological Institute business, Jerome Lectureship, thoughts on the School of Classical Studies' loss of prestige, qualities to look for in a director)
        - KWN - KO (Box 15, Reel 5773)
        - Koyle, George Simpson (Trustee), 1933-1938 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (Nominating Committee business)
        - La Farge, C. Grant (Secretary), 1923-1931 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (includes correspondence about student housing, administrative suggestions for operations in Rome, successor to director Stevens)
        - LAI - LEO (Box 15, Reel 5773)
        - Lewis, Naphtalie (Fellow), 1926 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (correspondence discussing Lewis' need to return home to his ailing mother, arrangements for him to continue fellowship work in New York)
        - Lockwood, Dean P. (Annual Professor, School of Classical Studies), 1924-1936 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (includes correspondence concerning his appointment; report of observations on students, academic standards, how best to help the cause of classics in America, admissions process, and summer session)
        - Lord, Louis E. (Secretary, Advisory Council; Annual Professor, School of Classical Studies), 1922-1932 (Box 15, Reel 5773)
          (includes list of names and addresses of Classical School students, 1896-1921; also, correspondence concerning summer session)
        - LORD, M - MA (Box 15, Reel 5773)
        - McClellan, George B. (Trustee; Vice President; Chairman, Committee on the Library), 1930-1939 (Box 15, Reel 5773-5774)
          (letter addressing Professor Sanders' complaints about the library, appointment of new librarian, nominating committee business)
        - McDaniel, Walton Brooks (Chairman, Advisory Council), 1928 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (copy of his article about the proper functions of the School of Classical Studies, correspondence about distribution of the article)
        - McKibben, William T. (Fellow), 1940-1941 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (correspondence about whether to conduct his fellowship research at home or postpone it until he can travel to Rome when the war is over)
        - Mead, William R. (President), 1927 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (includes correspondence concerning the advisory council's perception that the Classical School receives short shrift, administration and staffing of Classical School, housing of students and staff, fellowships, library)
        - Mendell, Clarence W. (Trustee; Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1928-1942 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (correspondence about publications, successor to director Stevens, fellows, library, staffing, summer session, Greek trip, advisory council, proposal to suspend fellowships and subscriptions from colleges until after the war)
        - MES - MU (Box 15, Reel 5774)
        - Ogle, Marbury R. (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1930-1939 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (includes letters concerning his appointment, fellows, library, administration and staffing, finances)
        - Ohl, Raymond T., 1936-1937 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (correspondence about summer session)
        - Oldfather, William A. (Chairman, Advisory Council), 1930-1934 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (includes correspondence about staffing, appointment as annual professor and his inability to accept, finances, librarian, fellowships)
        - OLS - PRA (Box 15, Reel 5774)
        - Prescott, Henry W., 1939-1940 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (correspondence regarding his appointment as Professor in Charge of the School of Fine Arts and ultimate decision not to fill the position due to war conditions)
        - Rand, E. K. (Trustee; Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1922-1939 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (correspondence concerning staffing, administration, advisory council, library, summer school)
        - RO - SAM (Box 15, Reel 5774)
        - Sanders, Henry A. (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1927-1933 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (includes correspondence concerning his appointment, fellows, criticism of the library, housing, his decision to return to the University of Michigan)
        - Savage, Eugene F. (Trustee), 1933-1934 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
        - School of Classical Studies, Advisory Council, undated, 1937-1940 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (form letters, reports of meetings)
        - Semple, William T. (Trustee; Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1933-1939 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (correspondence concerning staffing, appointment of Professor in Charge, fellowships, nominations)
        - Shipley, F. W. (Annual Professor, School of Classical Studies), 1928-1937 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (correspondence regarding details of appointment as annual professor, advisory council business, appointment as Professor in Charge and inability to return to Rome for health reasons)
        - Showerman, Grant (Director, Summer Sessions), 1927-1934 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (includes correspondence about scheduling, staffing, letters from former summer session participants, enrollment, finances, Showerman Memorial Fund for book purchases in honor of his son)
        - Smith, James Kellum (Trustee, Chairman, Committee on the School of Fine Arts; President), 1933-1942 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (includes correspondence concerning fellows, public relations policy, finances, contributing colleges and universities, statement summarizing academy's preparations and response to changing international situation annd war conditions)
        - Stevens, Gorham Phillips (Director, Rome), 1921-1932 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (includes correspondence regarding plans for establishing a summer session, fellows, library, needs of landscape architects, finances)
        - TAV - TAYLOR, F. (Box 15, Reel 5774)
        - Taylor, Lily Ross (Professor in Charge, School of Classical Studies), 1933-1941 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (includes letter of appointment, correspondence about fellowships, finances, staff, student activities, nominating committee business)
        - TAYLOR, M. - WA (Box 15, Reel 5774)
        - West, Andrew F. (Trustee; Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1921-1926 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (includes correspondence about staffing)
        - Westerman, William L. (Trustee; Professor in Charge, School of Classical Studies; Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1923-1934 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
          (correspondence regarding staffing, Westerman's resignation from the board)
        - WH - Z (Box 15, Reel 5774)
      - Barry Faulkner (Trustee) (Box 15, Reel 5774)
        - General Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 15, Reel 5774)
        - Citizens Committee for the Army-Navy Triptych Project--Correspondence and Financial Records, undated, 1942-1945 (Box 15, Reel 5774-5775)
          (includes plan of work and instructions, correspondence with participating artists, correspondence with art schools interested in participating in the project)
        - Citizens Committee for the Army-Navy Triptych Project--Printed Matter, undated, 1942-1944 (Box 15, Reel 5775)
        - Post-War Planning (Committee on the School of Fine Arts and Association of Alumni), 1944-1946 (Box 15, Reel 5775)
          (ideas solicited from Committee on the School of Fine Arts and alumni on the future direction and scope of the academy's program)
      - Allan C. Johnson, Correspondence, undated, 1938-1946 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
        (includes correspondence with the chairman and members of the Committee on the School of Classical Studies, advisory council, and Professor in Charge concerning routine business; letters from scholars and alumni in response to request for ideas to aid in post-war planning for future direction and scope of the academy's program; also, correspondence about summer school, finances, staffing; list of fellows in classical studies, 1896-1940; Joint Committee on Classical and Mediaeval Studies business; letter of resignation from Professor in Charge Mason Hammond, with thoughts on Professor Van Buren; nominating committee business)
      - William M. Kendall (Box 16, Reel 5775)
        - General Correspondence, undated, 1902-1941 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
          (includes list of students with opinions of their work, contract and specifications for bowl of Manship fountain; also letters concerning the establishment of a summer school)
        - American Academy in Rome Diploma, 1920 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
        - American Academy in Rome Seal, 1912-1913, 1935 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
        - Boring, William A. (Treasurer), undated, 1918 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
        - Memorials (McKim, Morgan, etc.), 1922-1929 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
          (includes correspondence concerning inscription tablets and cost estimates)
        - Millet, Frank D. (Secretary), undated, 1908-1909 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
          (letter about fellows, Villa Aurelia, names proposed as trustees)
        - Richardson, Symmes, 1925 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
          (correspondence concerning purchase of property adjoining the academy)
        - Stevens, Gorham Phillips (Director, Rome), 1912-1935 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
          (includes correspondence about New Building, McKim Memorial, collaborative problem, purchase of adjoining property)
      - C. Grant La Farge, Correspondence, 1910-1911 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
        (includes text of addresses delivered at the annual dinner of the Architectural League of New York with C. Grant La Farge, Lloyd C. Griscom, John L. Cadwalader, Edwin H. Blashfield, and Frank Mile Day, speakers)
      - Edward P. Mellon, Endowment Committee Correspondence, 1919-1923 (Box 16, Reel 5775)
      - Charles Dyer Norton, Endowment Committee Correspondence, undated, 1913-1917, (3 folders) (Box 16, Reel 5775-5776)
      - Charles A. Platt, Correspondence, 1916-1928 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        (includes correspondence concerning fundraising for fellowship in landscape architecture, endowment fund, Committee on the School of Fine Arts business; also, correspondence about fellows, staff, collaborative problem, library, advisory council, fellowship competition, Atelier)
      - John Russell Pope, Correspondence, 1926-1933 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        (includes correspondence concerning Committee on the School of Fine Arts business, going away gift for Director Stevens, finances)
      - Edward K. Rand, Correspondence, 1922-1923, 1928 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        (includes correspondence about irregularities in Mr. Laurie's accounts, Carter's death, fellows, controversy concerning a male and female student traveling together unchaperoned)
      - John C. Rolfe, Committee on Publications Correspondence, 1927 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
      - James Kellum Smith, Correspondence, 1937 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        (includes Committee on the School of Fine Arts business, exhibitions, publicity, activities of fellows, library, nominating committee business)
      - S. Breck Trowbridge (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Committee on the School of Fine Arts Correspondence, undated, 1915-1924 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Endowment Committee, General Committee Business, 1913-1921 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Endowment Committee, Fundraising Correspondence, undated, 1919-1920 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Endowment Committee, Loan Exhibition of Italian Masters [March 6-11, Fine Arts Bldg., 215 W. 57th St.], 1920 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Endowment Committee, Horatio Parker Fellowship, 1923 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
      - Ferruccio Vitale (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - General Correspondence, 1921-1923 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Collaborative Problem, 1921-1925 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Endowment Campaign, Fundraising Correspondence, 1919-1922, undated (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Endowment Campaign, Fundraising Events, Italy America Society Dinner, 1920 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Endowment Campaign, Fundraising Events, Loan Exhibition of Italian Masters, 1920 (Box 16, Reel 5776)
        - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture, Competitions, 1919-1930 (Box 16, Reel 5776-5777)
        - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture, Correspondence, 1919-1930 (Box 16, Reel 5776-5777)
        - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture, Fundraising, 1919-1930 (Box 16, Reel 5776-5777)
        - Fellowship in Landscape Architecture, Recipients (Edward Lawson, Ralph Griswold, Norman Newton, Richard Webel), 1919-1930 (Box 16, Reel 5776-5777)
        - Guernsey, Roscoe (Executive Secretary), 1920-1923 (Box 16, Reel 5777)
      - John Quincy Adams Ward, Correspondence, 1897-1898 (Box 16, Reel 5777)
        (includes notification of election to the board, letters concerning purchase of Villa Aurora)
      - Andrew F. West, Correspondence, 1918 (Box 16, Reel 5777)
        (concerns Professor Curtis's salary)
      - William L. Westerman, Correspondence, 1923-1935 (Box 16, Reel 5777)
        (includes correspondence about the Jerome lectureship, rumors that a woman may be appointed Professor in Charge of Classical Studies, staffing, finances, controversy over proposed publication of a fellow's dissertation, diplomas for fellows, excavations, details of Professor Ogle's appointment, library, publication committee business, advisory council)
- New York Office, 1855-circa 1981, undated, Series 3:; (box 17-32; 15 linear ft.)
  Since its founding the American Academy in Rome has maintained offices in New York. This office supports the work of the board of trustees and its many committees, and is responsible for administration of fellowship competitions, fundraising, and record keeping.
  The series is organized into seven subseries.
  3.1: Records of Staff, 1919-1950, undated
  3.2: Rosters, 1895-1939, undated
  3.3: Printed Matter, 1905-circa 1981
  3.4: Photographs, 1891-1941, undated
  3.5: Personal Papers, Memorabilia and Ephemera, 1855-1923, undated
  3.6: Association of the Alumni of the American Academy in Rome, 1913-1945, undated
  3.7: Miscellaneous Records, 1899-1926, undated
  - Records of Staff, 1919-1950, undated, 3.1:
    Records of staff include the office files of executive secretaries Roscoe Guersney, Meriwether Stuart, and Mary T. Williams; librarian George K. Boyce; and endowment fund campaign secretaries Phillilps B. Robinson and Edgar I. Williams.
    The executive secretary, based in New York, handled nearly all routine administrative matters. Records of this office (8 linear feet) are mainly those of Roscoe Guernsey (7.33 linear feet), who held the post from 1919 to 1946; they represent the most extensive and comprehensive set of files among all of American Academy in Rome records. Prior to 1919, this type of information is found among the records kept by the Secretary and, to a slightly lesser extent, the president. Records of two later executive secretaries, Meriwether Stuart and Mary T. Williams, are less comprehensive (each 0.33 linear feet).
    Other staff records are those of the librarian (2 folders) and endowment fund campaign secretaries (0.25 linear ft.). Although the library and its staff are based in Rome, records of George K. Boyce (former fellow in classical studies who was appointed librarian in 1939) are placed with those of the New York office staff because they are from the period when the academy was closed during the Second World War and all correspondence concerning library matters was addressed to him at the academy's New York office.
    Records of the executive secretaries are first in the series, followed by the files of the librarian and the endowment fund campaign secretaries. For each individual correspondence files are followed by files arranged alphabetically by subject or name of the person to whom the file relates.
    - Roscoe Guernsey (Executive Secretary) (Box 17, Reel 5777)
      - Correspondence, General, undated, 1919-1945 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
      - Abbott, Frank Frost (Trustee), 1916-1921 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
        (includes letters concerning Committee on Efficiency, Committee on Publications business)
      - Adams, Herbert (Trustee), 1936 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
      - Aldrich, Amey (sister of Director and official hostess during his tenure; Acting Director, Rome), 1937, 1941-1942 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
        (includes correspondence concerning research and publication of her history of Villa Aurelia, suggestions for management of academy while operations were suspended during World War II)
      - Aldrich, Chester H. (Committee on the School of Fine Arts; Director, Rome), 1933-1941) (Box 17, Reel 5777)
        (includes correspondence about Committee on the School of Fine Arts business, appointment of Aldrich as director, finances, fellows, staffing, competitions, exhibitions, summer session, housing, publications, library, letters of sympathy on Aldrich's death, memorial service plans)
      - Alumni Exhibitions, undated, 1919-1923 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
        (includes prospectus, unpublished checklist of 1919 exhibition, inquiries about circulating the exhibitions)
      - American Commission for the Protection and Salvage of Artistic and Historic Monuments in Europe, 1943 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
        (concerns approval of resolution offering academy facilities to the commission)
      - Annuities (TIAA), 1923-1945 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
        (concerning annuity payments for Roscoe Guernsey and Professor Van Buren)
      - Appointments, Elections, and Acceptances, 1921-1938 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
        (regarding trustees, officers, committees)
      - Armed Forces Master Records, Inc., undated, 1943-1944 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
        (correspondence concerning establishing libraries of recorded music for use by service men)
      - Armour, George A. (Trustee), 1915-1920 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
      - Atelier, undated, 1927-1933 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
        (includes outline of plan for Atelier to be operated by the academy for use by visiting architects, painters, and sculptors; list of books to be purchased for the reference library, should the Atelier be open to women, notice of student arrivals and departures)
      - Baldwin, Henry de Forest (Trustee), 1940 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
      - Beebe, Dwight S. (Trustee; Finance Committee), 1942-1945 (Box 17, Reel 5777)
      - Benton, Hale P. (Assistant to Director, Rome), 1926-1945 (Box 17, Reel 5777-5778)
        (includes correspondence concerning appointment and responsibilities, publications, shipment of student works, budget, list of equipment for sculptors' studio, health insurance for fellows, reports on library and administrative work that continued while the academy was closed during World War II, provisions for his retirement)
      - Boring, William A. and Crane, Arthur H. (Treasurer and Assistant Treasurer), 1919-1938 (Box 18, Reel 5778)
        (includes correspondence regarding extension of fellowship time, classification of subscribers, collaborative prize competition, Boring's report as visiting professor of fine arts, housing for Professor Sanders and family, pianos for Rome, endowment fund, staffing, biographical notes, resolution upon his death)
      - Boyce, George K. (Librarian), 1929-1940 (Box 18, Reel 5778)
        (includes correspondence about his appointment, news of library staff and activities, plans in the event that war conditions force the academy to close, Boyce's return to the U.S.)
      - Bradford, Lindsay (Treasurer), 1945-1946 (Box 18, Reel 5778)
      - Broadcasts, 1935-1942 (Box 18, Reel 5778)
        (concerns broadcasts of works by winners of the Prix de Rome in musical composition, also arrangements for announcements of upcoming competitions)
      - Budget, 1931/32-1945/46 (Box 18, Reel 5778)
      - Carpenter, Rhys (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1939-1945 (Box 18, Reel 5778)